Look, we've got
the submissions as read. I don't know if you've
seen the other parties'
submissions as well that we're considering this morning, because there's a bit of a
competition of ideas in there, and we might well ask you questions about what you
think about some of their comments.
But what I'll do is I'll set the time for 10 minutes.
Sure.
And I'll give you a call with four to go if you're still going.
Take the submission as read.
And we do like asking questions, there's probably quite a few.
So, in your hands.
Sure. No problem. Well, thank you, and kia ora tātou. Thank you for having me.
Leonard Samson, Chief Executive of Port of Tauranga.
Look, just
from a port perspective,
Port of Tauranga, we fundamentally oppose extending the Local Government
Informations
Act.
Fundamentally, our view is that the existing commercial accountability
arrangements are fit for purpose, and that the bill would create unnecessary
commercial, legal, and security risks.
The application of the LGOIMA incorrectly treats port companies as
council-controlled organizations when they are commercially
governed businesses.
The purpose of the LGOIMA is to support democratic participation and
accountability in local government objectives, and they do not align
with the port company's commercial mandate.
The commercial mandate of port companies aligns with the Port Companies Act
1998,
and it requires ports to operate as successful commercial businesses and provides
accountability measures that are suited to that purpose.
This was a deliberate governance model that Parliament
intentionally created to commercially govern ports and preserve the
agility, confidentiality to promote effective competition in
freight markets.
Another added complexity for Port of Tauranga is that its listed
issuer status as an NZX-listed
company with public and private shareholders, we're already subject to
significant market disclosure and shareholder obligations.
Moving away from the current arrangements would impact
investor confidence. Applying public sector information regimes
could disrupt shareholder relationships, commercial
confidentiality, and investor confidence.
It is also not comparable with other partially publicly owned
businesses operating in competitive markets.
For example, Air New Zealand, Mercury Energy, are not subject to the
comparable official information regimes.
The existing
accountability, reporting, audits, and regulatory oversight and shareholder
scrutiny already provide significant transparency without the need
to extend to further LGOIMA requirements.
And finally, there is no clear or proportionate case.
It's not clear from the bill
that's evidenced any accountability failure, and
it's hard to understand the purposes behind the broad intervention and
disproportionate issue that is claimed.
That's the basis for my submission, so I don't need to take up the full 10 minutes.
I'm happy to take any questions.
Excellent. There's a lot of value in question time. So I'll start with Dan.
Hey, thank you, Leonard. Really good to have your submission and
before our committee today. As a listed
company, I guess there's already a huge amount of
disclosure requirements. Can you kind of elaborate for the
committee
the extent of information requirements that any listed
company has
to the public and to its shareholders?
Fundamentally, there's a continuous disclosure requirement that means anything that
can be considered material, and that material test is
significant. So anything that could be considered to have
a... And it is a test that could have any
influence, whether it be in terms of investor confidence, share
price, et cetera, we need to make disclosures.
So even as simple as
we are employing a new executive team member, we're just about in the process of
looking to make, we need to make that listed issuer disclosure.
Any fundamental changes, any new business
we secure that could be significant to the port and have
an influence
flow through to share price, that needs to require a disclosure.
Any change to governance, any new directors.
So
it's hard to go and list every example because in a lot of cases,
it's pretty much everything anyway.
It's anything that could be considered to be material.
And that material test is not
binary and you err on the side of caution because anything
can be considered material in a lot of cases.
Yeah, thank you. And maybe a second question, if I can, Mr.
Chair, is
as part of your requirements, you run annual general meetings.
I'm assuming they are robust forums
for
your shareholders. Is that correct?
That's correct. We hold
twice
a year interim, so we have an interim and a full year
investor day analyst briefings. And so providing, making sure, and
that's available to all investors.
And so, shareholders have representation at those there.
We also hold annual AGMs, and they are very robust,
with plenty of time for shareholders to go and
participate in terms of questions in advance and
be involved in the governance of the port.
Thank you very much.
Carlos.
Hi. Thank you.
I just wonder if this law is passed, what is the extra or
additional operational cost will it create?
Or how will these changes affect the efficiency and
productivity?
There's a significant impact to--
I guess,
there's a significant administration burden that would be associated with it.
And you would potentially continually be running the test over what's commercially
sensitive and what's not. And so, in a lot of cases when you talk about
from a port company perspective, the model, it
was a deliberate model that was put in place with the Port Companies Act to
actually preserve confidentiality and provide
effective competition within the freight
market. So from
a Legoyma perspective, for example, the international shipping lines, all of those
type of things, you could find yourself being in significant areas where you're
having to redact
a lot of time,
things that could be considered commercially sensitive.
Just the administration function in itself would be a significant burden on
our organization. In terms of impact, in terms of
specifically port productivity, I'm
not sure. And while we support absolute transparency around the
reporting of port productivity figures, this is not the
pathway to do that in terms of the Legoyma pathway.
That is something that there's a separate, as you note here,
Andy. There's a separate piece of work going on in terms
of an inquiry into port company productivity
that should be looking to go and address those type of outcomes.
But the Legoyma requirement won't have any measurable
impact whatsoever in terms of port productivity.
Thank you.
I've got a few questions too. Just first of all, because this comes
out of
the point that you are partially, or all ports are at least partially owned
by-
Yes
... local bodies. The relationship you have with Quayside Holdings,
how could you characterize that? Is it active, passive? What is it?
It's an active relationship. It's a very good relationship.
I guess what I will say here is
the mandate of Quayside, if you like to act as
the custodian or the asset owner of
regional assets,
and with an independent commercial mandate to operate those as
intergenerational investment entities, has effectively acted
as a buffer between
local government, local body politics, if you like, and running a port
operation. Quayside fundamentally make our lives a lot easier
by having an intermediary
in between the Port of Tauranga and the ultimate shareholder
being the regional council. And it allows the Port of Tauranga to focus on
running its business, which is actually running a port operational business and
doing the best we can in terms of providing services to our customers,
and obviously running our business and playing our part in the
community.
No, thanks. Are they subject to Legoyma,
Quayside?
Good question. They will be CCAP potentially.
I'm not entirely sure.
Okay. It'd be good actually if we can understand that because-
I can come back and clarify that for you. Yes.
Yeah, because there are a number of holding companies which hold port assets across
the country, and other assets as well.
Second area of question I just wanted to ask.
In the Port Companies Act, there's the requirement, as you said, and deliberate
requirement of the legislation to act as a successful business, and that is the
only stipulation there. If you look at the definition of
what they usually use definition of successful business, it is not purely
commercial. It's a multiplicity of things which
includes good customer relations, good relations with community,
all that sort of stuff. What's your view of what being a
successful business is and is not?
Well, I think yes,
a successful organization is more than just the commercial
outcomes. But the fact that a commercial is in there, to me
indicates that there needs to be a level of
capital discipline applied to those businesses,
that would be consistent with it being
in a private setting. And I guess what I mean to that, that is one area
that you have the Auditor General as the auditor for the port companies, and
actually holding port companies to account for the capital decisions that they
make. And again, another point I want to raise here,
as
a listed entity is we have those capital disciplines forced upon
us by being a listed entity. We make poor capital decisions, we
see it in our share price the very next day.
We're accountable to our shareholders at any point in time
as and when we make those decisions.
And as I mentioned before, with the
continuous disclosure requirements, any significant capital decisions will
trigger those requirements.
Cool. And look, I wanted to ask one other question because, certainly in our
inquiry and discussions, there is one particular project which you've got on the
go,
which I think we're all vitally interested in, which is the Stella Passage project.
Well, first of all, I'm interested in how you're getting on, but I'm also
interested in how that project would be affected
were it subject to Legoyma.
It's hard to know the nature of the-- It would open up to all
realms of different types of
scrutiny and questioning, and some of which you're going through
a process, whether it be an environmental process and
now in a fast-track panel process that there's a lot of discussions
that are covered under, I guess, in some cases privileged.
So I'm not sure.
But
frankly, I don't think it helps that process at all,
because
I'm not sure what additional transparency you'd have.
Just to answer your first part of your question, which was how are we going in that
process? We just spent three days In a hearing
by the fast-track panel, and
so we await a decision by September.
Excellent. I wish you well.
Thank you.
Thank you. Any other questions, colleagues?
No. Thank you. Look, what I was looking for there was just to understand whether
you thought that would intrude even more into that process.
And look, I will ask tame-
I think inevitably it would do, because you- But without
understanding the nature of the types of
questions that will get asked, inevitably it would.
Yeah.
That would further go and potentially delay it.
I've got a question.
Okay. Tracy's got one other question.
Just because you've raised that.
And then I've got one. Yeah.
It's certainly my understanding that the bill doesn't change any of your
existing reporting obligations.
It just adds something extra. So under the
Auditor-General and the Companies Act, and all of the ways in which you already
assume you have public accountability, do you
have to report on environmental effects, on workplace
practices, on any kind of relationship with public owners?
I say that because I noted that you say that you
describe yourself as
a privately owned business, acknowledging the fact that you are
54% owned by the public essentially.
So
do you already disclose or report on those other factors-
Yes
... or are those the ones-
Yeah, we do. Yeah, absolutely. We disclose annually in our annual
report, we'll always disclose our health and safety metrics. We'll disclose...
We've got extensive environmental metrics that we've developed over the past years.
And again, I guess from our perspective, there are obviously
more and more in terms of ESG requirements, and obviously we're subject to
climate related disclosures
as a listed entity. And so again, that brings a whole another layer of
transparency and reporting requirements that are mandated.
But even in the ones that are not mandated, we already provide all of those in
terms of health and safety,
workplace
reporting. We provide all of that information today and that level of
transparency.
Right. Thank you.
And look, the other question I was going to ask, because it is one that we've
traversed elsewhere, is the issues around transparency of charges.
So whether it's gate charges, port charges, whatever it might be.
We've heard some sort of light touch, com type arrangements,
which some ports essentially say they subject themselves to
already. Have you got a view on how best those charging
regimes might be made as transparent as possible?
Where you would go, where you wouldn't go.
I
guess you go back to the Port Companies Act that requires to operate as a
commercial successful business.
I think if you looked at the port sector across the board, there's not that many
port companies in the entire country that are operating what you would
consider successful commercial businesses.
There are a number of port companies that are operating in negative free cash flow.
So from a
net perspective,
I'm not sure that there's a fundamental issue there.
But port companies, we
have regular
publishing of our tariffs are available on our website.
I'm just not sure in terms of if your question then relates to the
transparency, are they available?
Yes, they're publicly available
at any point in time, but there's always a process that you go through with our
customers in those discussions, and I suspect each port
company as
its own business needs to go and undertake those processes.
Yeah. Okay. No, that's really helpful. Thank you, Leonard.
Really appreciate the time. Really appreciate the submission and wish you well for
September.
Thank you very much. Thank you for having me.
Thanks, Leonard. Thank you.
Cheers. Bye.
Right. Okay, now we've got the Maritime Union of New Zealand who are
also on Zoom.
Morning Clint, Carl, and Rob.
Morning.
Good to see you there. I'm getting an
echo there. Anyway,
we've got you down for 10 minutes. You can take the submission as read.
Anything you want to highlight, really appreciate that.
There'll be plenty of questions, and I think there'll be some cross-referencing of
questions between the various submissions, so I don't know if you've read the other
submissions that we've got in front of us at the moment, but
each of you is challenging each other's positions, so it's all good.
So we look forward to what you've got to say.
I'll give you a call with four minutes to go.
We may go a little bit of a stretch over, but, we'll try not to.
But, yeah, in your hands.
Excellent. Well, thank you very much for having us. We appreciate it.
Really appreciate the time and being here.
Yeah, as you say, our submission speaks for itself and,
I won't hold up too much of the time, just yet.
I'll hand it over to Rob and Clint to go through it in a bit more finer
detail and chip in a bit later on. Thank you.
Thank you, Carl.
So our view is that ports are strategic national assets.
But despite being fully or partially
council owned and key nodes in our transport network, there is
input from the normal transparency that applies to other strategic transport assets
like NZTA.
Even privately owned asset holders like electricity lines companies and airports
are subject to more oversight through the Commerce Commission that doesn't apply to
seaports.
Responding to some of the issues raised by the previous
submitter,
not all ports are listed on the NZX, and the
transparency requirements of the NZX are fundamentally different from
official information legislation.
As he himself alluded to,
with his
claims that
complying with official information disclosure would be burdensome.
Now, responding to that point, I'm a school board chair.
We're a small school. We are subject to disclosure under
the Official Information Act. We have to do that.
If a small school can manage it, I think a large port can.
The costs are relatively minor and transparency is important.
The issues with the The lack of transparency in the current regime was exemplified
by Ports of Auckland's lack of transparency during the 2012
lockout and during their disastrous automation project.
This bill is timely
because as the committee has recently heard during the ports inquiry, New Zealand
is moving towards a hub and spoke model port organization where
international vessels will service only a few key ports and freight
will be transported between those ports and regional spokes by coastal vessels.
That is going to happen whether it is a government-led process or imposed
on us by international shipping lines.
A hub and spoke model to be successful for New Zealand will require a national
port strategy and greater coordination of investment between
ports and
with government to ensure we have the infrastructure where we need it
and that we need. That won't be possible if ports continue to act as
if they're simple, private, isolated identities like the corner shop
rather than the strategic assets in our transport network that they are.
So this bill will help put New Zealand in a better place
for the reality that we are facing in the port sector as we move
towards a hub and spoke model.
The one
amendment that MANZ has suggested would be to ensure that private
operators are also covered by the disclosure regime.
The prospect of privatization of port operations, as is currently being
proposed for Lyttelton, should not become a loophole to avoid
transparency and stymie coordination.
And
we see that being a real risk
that
the transparency that's needed and that this bill would help to
accomplish
would be stymied if we see private operators exempted from it.
Thank you.
You good for questions?
Yes.
Okay, cool. Right. Questions, colleagues. Tracy.
Thanks.
Thank you, and thank you for your submission.
Can you give me some examples of what sort of specific information
that you've been unable to
obtain from ports that you
would have liked to have?
Well, the Ports of Auckland automation process was
a huge example of where hundreds of millions of dollars of
what was ultimately ratepayers' money was wasted by port
management who had this--
They wanted to de-unionize the port, and they
had this vainglorious idea of themselves.
During that process,
the union was largely shut out.
De-unionizing the port was part of the goal of the automation process, and
councilors also found it hard to get information out of the port what was
happening. Our belief is that if there had been greater
transparency during that automation process, then the alarm
bells would've been able to be sounded much earlier, before all that money was
wasted, before
the lives of workers were lost.
Yeah. I've got an example of actually being at a hearing with the council,
where elected councilors were asking the
CEO
at the time, during the dispute in 2012,
some questions, and he just kept hiding behind the corporate veil, saying it was
sensitive information
that he couldn't share because it had implications to the
company. And
as we all know the result of what that carry on
did to
the port.
And so
it really has to stop, this covering up and hiding behind
that corporate veil. The
community should be able to ask questions and get straight
answers.
There's got to be some accountability. That's what we're after.
And I don't think it's necessarily just the community either in discussions.
We talked about this during the ports inquiry and discussions we had with the
Infrastructure Commission last year.
They also described difficulty mapping in terms of
getting the information to map what is effectively incredibly vital infrastructure.
So
that speaks to the need to plan and,
as Clint said, the fact that lack of transparency stymies the ability to
plan at a national level.
Yeah.
Can I ask two questions? The first one of them is, the Port of Auckland, obviously,
who you focused on, because I know obviously the history there,
is not subject to the same kind of disciplines that the NZX were put on
that
Port Taranaki was just talking about.
If the same discipline were required, anything that's commercially
significant and obviously the investment that was being made and
the automation would've absolutely been in that category, so would any risks to
that associated with that. That would make that actually
ironically more transparent than it was
by the looks of it. Would that be fair?
I'm not advocating for a second for
privatization, but what I am wondering aloud about is whether in fact
if that same discipline was there for the non-privatized,
the fully publicly owned companies, whether that would actually make a difference.
Well, obviously there is greater transparency, but it's a particular kind of
transparency.
This
bill would allow
greater discourse, greater inquiry.
We don't see that the disclosures that you get on
the NZX are necessarily
completely aligned with the disclosure that you would need, for instance,
in making a national assessment across all ports.
It is better, but it's not
necessarily fit for purpose. It's a sort of halfway measure or
a tool with a different purpose.
And that takes me to the other question I was going to ask, which is, we've
certainly had quite a number of conversations around the port
inquiry, which have gone to the transparency for things like charging
regimes, et cetera, investment regimes and so on.
Whether the Commerce Commission has a light touch or a heavier touch
oversight of ports is, I think, a live question that's been
raised with us.
What it seems is that the LGOIMA, I'm well aware of from a local government point
of view, is exceedingly intrusive.
Possibly more than anybody actually realizes who's made submissions, because I've
been on the other end of it, I know how intrusive it is.
But at the moment we've got
such a light touch, in your view anyway, that you're not getting the information
that's needed. Is there a halfway house, I guess is what I'm
asking you.
And it may be through a range of different pieces of legislation.
Yeah. You're right that the Commerce
Commission, if they had powers over the seaports, could
require disclosure of information that's not publicly disclosable now.
That's not the question that's in front of us.
Right.
We see that there'll be real benefits to this, particularly as we move towards the
hub and spoke model. So, that's our focus now.
Okay, cool. Julianne. Oh, sorry.
It's worth noticing that in the LGOIMA there are still
reasonable protections for commercial sensitivity and the like.
It's not open slather.
Yeah. I know how it works.
Julianne.
Kia ora. Thank you so much for your submission.
I guess I just wanted to ask, do you think it would be
surprising that those organizations would show up to the
select committee and say, "Oh, no, we can't do this.
This would be a bad thing." Or is that something that we should
expect, and be a little more
understandable that they're defending their position to not have to comply with
something, however, there's still a good case for it?
Yeah. I'd say that the port's position is not surprising,
that they'd be opposed to greater transparency.
I think as the previous submitter showed, the
ethos of the ports tends to be that they're just private companies, just
the same as the corner dairy, the same as a factory making widgets.
Our view is that
they are not. They are strategic assets that all of
them have some level of public ownership, and they are vital to New
Zealand's economic future.
We are
moving towards this hub and spoke model, and they
are each crucial nodes in that hub and spoke, whether
they'll be spokes or hubs. So,
in our view, transparency is vital.
But it's not surprising that
their view accords to how they view themselves.
Cool. Look, thank you very much. Really appreciate it, and also really appreciate
all of the discussions through the inquiry process as well.
It's been most helpful to get all the input we've had.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Thanks, man.
You're welcome. Enjoy the rest of the day.
Okay.
Then we've got the NZCTU.
Who are also
on there.
Good morning.
Lovely to see you there.
Thank you.
So, I'll just clear that. We've got your submission, which you can take
as read.
You've got 10 minutes. I'll give you a call with four to go,
because we do like asking questions, as you've obviously heard.
And so, in your hands.
Very good. Well, thank you very much.
Tēnā koutou katoa, and thank you for the opportunity to speak to
the select committee on our submission
on the Local Government Ports Accountability Bill.
I'm Melissa Ransom-Bridges. I'm the Secretary of the New Zealand Council of Trade
Unions, and joining me is Corey Bourne, who is in our
policy team as a senior policy advisor.
We represent over 32 affiliated unions, including
MUNZ, who you just heard from. And also,
the RMTU, who I understand has also submitted on this bill.
And just to start off, we'd like to begin by saying that we endorse and
support the points made in their submissions.
Collectively, we represent over 370,000
working people across Aotearoa, New Zealand.
And we also acknowledge Te Tiriti o Waitangi as the founding document of
Aotearoa, and represent over 60,000 kaimahi
Maori through our affiliated unions as well.
So we support this bill. We see it as
a modest and practical and also an important
step to bring port companies into the same accountability
framework as other council-controlled organizations.
Ports are publicly owned and publicly connected
critical infrastructure, and decisions about them can have
major consequences for workers, for local
communities, for regional economies, supply
chains, iwi and hapū, and also for the
environment. These decisions should therefore be
made with appropriate transparency, accountability, and
also, importantly for us, regard to good employment practice.
We consider that this bill helps achieve that without
undermining any commercial role of port companies.
I'm going to hand over now to Corey to go through our submission
in a bit more detail. And also obviously for
even more detail, we defer to MUNZ and RMTU, who have a
particularly
good understanding of the issues at play in this legislation. Thank you.
Now, Kia ora, select committee . As Mel opened with, the
accountability and transparency critical to port companies' social license to
operate. They operate and occupy significant public
infrastructure on public land, public assets, and they are delivering
essential services.
I'm sure you'll probably hear this a lot today, but we know that 99% of the
country's international trade by volume comes through our ports.
So we're not here to dispute that they're not cr-- they are critical
infrastructure, both regionally and nationally.
The scale and impact of their operations are very diverse.
So they're large employers in their local communities.
And with port land use on the waterfront, it means there are relevant environmental
and cultural factors, and therefore a number of different interests in the
governance of these assets.
We think the bill introduces some fairly minor changes that will help with the
accountability to those local interests, and note that submission of
demands around ensuring that those privately operated
ports aren't
out of scope of those provisions, too.
We would suggest that this bill isn't creating new obligations out of nowhere,
applies those existing understood rules from the
LGOIMA that other entities already work
within. We're not looking at special treatment for
the ports, just to remove that historical exemption that's seen them left out.
And as we heard from Munz, that there is those withholding grounds built
in. Andy, you were saying that you feel like it is quite
intrusive, but there are grounds there around withholding information and
if there's
too much to disclose, those protections are there, we would
suggest.
Secondly, just want to talk briefly to the importance of supporting good work that
this bill seeks to do. Unsurprisingly, we're widely focused
on supporting good work, which is mahi that has a lasting positive
impact on the worker, the employer, the wider community.
Good work means, among other things, fair wages, health and safe work,
productive and cooperative workplaces, and meaningful and fulfilling work that
contributes to society.
We are therefore supportive of this bill to help port companies and their
workforces realize good work.
They're more and more understanding these days that businesses operate beyond a
narrow view of profit margins and the operations impact the workforces and the
communities that they are based in.
Again, suggesting that this bill is just bringing ports into that already
established framework and not trying to overhaul the regulatory framework around
them, but support them to be locally beneficial and accountable
operations. My background's health and safety, so I'm going to focus on
that as one aspect of good work. Port work is
physically demanding, it's high risk, often involves shift work and other forms
of work like that. It means that we
see some serious health and safety issues, fatigue, moving plant and
vehicles, rail operations, working at heights, among others.
These have fatal consequences if governance is poor.
Alongside worker engagement, good governance is the critical
element of successful workplace health and safety.
In our written sub, we highlighted the turnaround of the operations at Ports of
Auckland as something that regulatory settings should support.
Ports of Auckland had that horrendous health and safety record with some severe
failings that led to worker fatalities and then first HSWA
conviction of an officer.
But that turnaround, that was bringing good governance and the workforce of Ports
of Auckland together and saw the port significantly increase its
productivity,
and at the same time dramatically increasing employee engagement.
So we think those are the kind of settings that regulatory settings should try and
support and practice. And while the bill, we say it's only light touch, but we
think it will slightly move the needle in that way.
And just want to make the final point that good employment is not in competition
with commercial performance. In fact, it's the opposite that's often
true, where productive businesses are those that work with their employees, they're
safe, and they are productive.
Beyond the employment sphere,
we think it's important for ports to demonstrate social and environmental
responsibility by having regard to the interests of the community in which they
operate.
We think regulatory settings should support the ports to work
with their workforce, their local communities, including iwi and hapū, to
mitigate their impacts on the environment and continue to maintain their social
license to operate. On that basis, we recommend that-
We've got about three and a half minutes left.
Just finishing. Final sentence.
Oh
We are recommending that the bill
passes for that balanced approach to transparency and accountability of these
critical assets and for supporting the ports to be good employers for everyone's
benefit. Thank you for your time.
Thank you both. Colleagues, looking for questions. Tracy.
Thank you.
Just going back to health and safety, given that it's a particular penchant of
yours, can you give me any practical kind of
examples of how having
better direct access to information around health and safety
could help, not just identify, but perhaps prevent
accidents or encourage better ways of working?
Is there an end game here?
I think that when we're talking about health and safety, we're talking around that
good employment governance piece.
But to the point around information sharing, that is a critical element of
good health and safety as well, right?
When you're engaging the workers and they need to
know what the
decision-making processes are, what the issues are that we're actually trying to
address. So having as much information as possible is helpful
when you're collaborating on health and safety responses to things
on the ports.
Okay, thank you.
Two questions from me, if I can.
First one of them is, you've talked about in your written
submission
that at, two, the profit margins are the sole
concern.
Now, I note that the Port
Companies Act actually says operate a successful business.
Yeah.
As I understand, there is no legal Definition of successful business, but
it's generally accepted to be much more than profit.
It includes
health and safety, community, environment, all sorts of other things.
You're making a
statement there-
Right
... which I'm not sure is entirely true.
But would it be helpful to actually say that those things are,
in one way or the other, they are legally
what we expect a successful business to do, as opposed to just we assume that
that's what people think it means?
Yeah, I think so. And in the context of the introduction there, that's around
maybe some of the framework of setting those reforms of the '80s, where
profit margins were the sole driver, not necessarily that the ports only
have those. But I take your point.
Things might have evolved since then.
Yes. Yeah. I'm saying it's a relic of the time that they are outside
that scope.
So would it be helpful to be a bit more explicit about that expectation
that successful business does not just mean a financial bottom line, but more than
that?
Yes, I would agree with that.
Okay, cool. Thank you.
And then the other question I had was just,
you've made the comment also in your written submission, significant public
expenditure has been made to develop and maintain these built environments, i.e.
the ports themselves. I just wondered perhaps to what degree that's
true, that it's significant public investment's been put in.
It might have been a long, long time ago, but I don't know whether, if you like,
ratepayers have been putting money into ports
for quite a long time. I think it's been basically built on the business.
The one question I'd have on that context would be Port of Lyttelton, which if they
do a big development, the
ratepayer will be significantly involved in that discussion.
Mm-hmm.
But as a general statement, is that necessarily the case?
Or is the fact that it's been built on the business of the
customers effectively have been the ones that have been paying for it rather than
the ratepayer?
I think as you point out, Eddie, it might be a little bit of both-
Yeah
... the original setup. But then there are situations, as you say, where
expansion or changing in operations, there might be a question
of ratepayer input there as well.
Okay. One for us to think about. Look, really appreciate that. I'll just check.
I don't see any other questions, so thank you very much.
Really appreciate it.
Thanks for your time. Appreciate it.
Thank you.
Okay, and now we move to in-person for the
last three we've got.
So we have first up,
Ian. Welcome.
Morning, everyone.
And congratulations again on being the new port CEO, sir.
Oh, thank you very much.
Executive director.
Thanks for the opportunity, and hopefully something for the committee.
So again, take the submission as it is. We've got 10 minutes.
I'll give you a call with four to go.
All right. Thank you.
If we can scrape it over, then we scrape it over. We'll try not to.
All right. Good morning, everybody. Mr.
Chairman and members of the committee, my name is Ian Bonner, and I am the
Executive Director of the Port CEOs Group.
Thank you for the opportunity to appear before you today.
Our written submission was developed following consultation with the CEOs of all
13 commercial port companies represented by this organization.
While those ports differ significantly in ownership, scale, and
commercial model, there was unanimous agreement on the position before you
today.
Rather than repeat the written submission, I would like to briefly summarize why
the Port CEOs Group does not support the bill in its current form, and then propose
an alternative path forward. Our concerns can be
summarized in three points.
First, as you've already heard, Parliament deliberately established the port
companies to operate as commercial businesses, and designed an
accountability regime around that.
Exclusion from LogOIMA was not an oversight.
It was intentional and reflects the reality of port operations.
Secondly, and I want to be very clear here, the ports are
not resistant to transparency.
We support the objective of strong public accountability, but we do not
believe the bill has demonstrated that the existing accountability
framework is materially failing.
And thirdly, should it be concluded that even greater
transparency is desirable,
we do not believe this legislation will deliver the transparency or public
understanding you are seeking.
So I'd like to begin with the legislative context.
The current framework is not an accident.
The Port Companies Act states that the principal objective of every port
company is to operate as a successful business.
So ports compete with each other for freight, they
compete for shipping services, they negotiate commercial contracts,
make large long-term infrastructure investments,
and they increasingly compete internationally as part of global supply
chains.
Parliament recognized that publicly owned ports could remain publicly accountable
while operating under commercial disciplines, rather than as
extensions of local government administration.
This bill would alter that balance.
In our view, such a change should be supported by a clearly
identified policy problem and evidence that the existing framework
is no longer achieving Parliament's original intent.
We are not persuaded that that threshold has been met.
The port sector fully accepts that public accountability matters.
The question is not whether ports should be accountable, they already are.
As our written submission sets out, ports already operate within
extensive accountability arrangements through shareholder oversight, company law,
environmental regulation, health and safety regulation, maritime
regulation, continuous disclosure obligations for listed companies,
and a range of existing public reporting requirements.
If you consider that there are genuine accountability gaps, we would welcome that
discussion. But we do not believe that the bill clearly identifies where the
existing framework has failed or why changing the model
established by Parliament is the appropriate response
More information does not necessarily produce more transparency.
The first reading debate focused appropriately on transparency.
We are not resistant to transparency, but transparency is not
an end in itself. Its purpose is to improve accountability and
public understanding. The committee should therefore ask not
simply whether the bill might produce more information, it should ask whether it
will produce better understanding.
Legoyma provides access to information held by individual
organizations, but many of the questions you raised are not questions
about individual port companies, they're questions about the freight
system as a whole.
Are infrastructure investments properly coordinated?
Is the network resilient? Do we have the right balance between pricing,
resilience, and competition? Do ports, rail, and shipping
services work together effectively?
These are all legitimate questions, but they cannot be answered by
requesting additional documents from one port company at a time.
The challenge is not simply access to information, it is bringing
information together in a way that explains how the national freight system is
performing.
The bill may produce more information, but it's much less likely to produce more
understanding.
Indeed, there is a real risk that it produces fragmented information about
individual organizations without providing parliament or the
public with a coherent picture of the system that they are
actually interested in. Several members during the first reading
debate also referred to broader issues such as national freight strategy,
resilience, environmental performance, and the future role of ports.
These are important issues, but they reinforce the point.
These are system-level policy questions.
A requester-driven information regime applied to individual commercial
entities is not a substitute for a coherent national freight
strategy or nationally consistent reporting.
Similarly, the debate referred to expectations around environmental
responsibility and being a reasonable employer.
These are important objectives, but they are fundamentally
questions about how organizations should behave, not about access to
information.
If Parliament wishes to strengthen those obligations, they are best addressed
directly through the legislation governing those matters rather than
through an information access regime.
So,
as I said, port CEOs' group is not arguing against greater transparency.
If you conclude that additional transparency would improve public confidence,
we would welcome working constructively on a more targeted approach.
In our view, you should first identify the accountability
gap you wish to address, then consider what information would genuinely
improve public understanding, and then finally, design a framework capable of
delivering that outcome. In our view, that is more likely to
achieve this bill's underlying objective than extending a
requester-driven regime to individual port companies.
For those reasons, we respectfully recommend the bill does not
proceed in its current form. Thank you.
Thank you. We've got about four minutes left, but I think we will go a fraction
over here because I know there'll be a few questions.
So Tracey first, then Dan, then I've got some.
Thank you. And you ended up probably answering most of my questions.
Oh, okay. Well, no, that's fine.
But I think I've still got kind of one.
And look, I do have a lot of sympathy for the transparency v
accountability dichotomy that exists.
Yeah.
But if the CE sector is already sufficient as
affordability, are you able to identify any
information that the public can currently directly get from port companies
about things like major strategic, environmental safety or
employment sort of decisions? And how do they obtain that?
Yep. So there's a number of ways that they can get those sorts of bits of
information. So each of the ports publish their statement of corporate intent.
They publish annual reports.
In the case of the listed companies, they're responsible to
shareholders and AGMs.
But
in the case of those that aren't listed, they front up to their council
owners, and those are public meetings.
People are able to watch those and attend those,
and ask questions in some cases. And
so there's a number of different ways that people can get access to
information. I've worked in a number of different sectors, so I'm
relatively new to the sector. Thank you for the congratulations earlier.
I've got to say, I'm absolutely,
to use a Liverpool colloquialism, gobsmacked by the level
of operational information that is made publicly
available about the ports. Compared to other sectors that I've worked in,
there is vast amounts of data and information out there and available,
whether it's published through the Ministry of Transport or through other
mechanisms.
I actually think we've got the inverse problem.
We've got so much data, it's actually hard, and I'm sure you've found this as
you've worked through pulling your select committee report.
There's so much information out there, it's actually hard to distill themes from
it.
And you can
pretty much find a point of data to justify any
story that you want to tell.
So I think the big gap actually is not
port by port, that depth of information, it's more how does our whole
system hang together.
So if there's a disruption at one port, how does that then flow through to the rest
of the ports? And it's actually quite hard to see that picture.
I think that's the gap, and I don't think Legoyma would help us understand that any
better.
What is the fix for that then?
So
this is something I've picked up and I'm working with the CEs to try and
bring together some reporting that we put out ourselves,
and we can work with the officials on that.
One of the reasons why it's hard to
get a consistent picture is each of the ports over time have evolved
their own way of measuring,
right? So
Whether a vessel has arrived on time in one port is measured one way
and is measured a different way at a different port.
So we need to work together to get consistent on that.
So I think that's an opportunity. I think it will help everybody
understand how the network as a whole performs as we move
into the discussions around evolving a port strategy
and things like that. Yeah. A lot of my career was spent
in telco, actually. So
the comparison I see is you can see how little bits of the
network, the nodes of the network are all performing, but you can't see how the
network as a whole
actually responds to disruption and things like that, and that's the gap.
Mm.
And I really don't think that logoima is going to help us get any better with that.
Cool. Dan.
Thanks, Mr Chair. Ian, thanks to your organization, to your members for
your input on the ports inquiry.
Thank you.
We're certainly hoping to complete that very soon.
Just in your submission, you kind of paint a picture of
the implications of this if it moves forward.
I just wonder, if this moves forward, what impact will it have on the
commercial or profitability of some ports?
And of course, local councils rely on those ports
to fund their operations. What does this bill
have as an unintended consequence on port
profitability?
Yeah. I think there's three key parts to that.
So like we've touched on the fact that there is an administrative cost to
doing that.
But that's only part of the story.
Our ports, as you correctly said, there was a question about
how certain rate payer funding going into the ports.
No, the money flows the other way.
It flows to
their owners and help to keep rates down.
So they are negotiating the ports with some of the
biggest companies in the world, right?
So let's take
an international shipping line like Maersk, for example.
Maersk earns more in two days than our largest port,
Tauranga, makes all year. So
handing Maersk the ability to actually request further,
more detailed information during a negotiation process with the
ports
makes that relationship even more imbalanced than it is currently.
So we have to remember that these are, in many cases,
giant commercial organizations that are incredibly well-resourced.
So there's that.
Another thing that
I would suggest the committee should bear in mind is the chilling effect
that counterparties, whoever they may be,
will share at the moment their commercial information with ports
about shipping forecasts and predicted
freight volumes and so forth.
Now, those could be carved out with the commercial exemption,
but if you're one of those counterparties, you may choose not to share that,
because you don't know exactly how it'll be treated, and that will also hurt the
efficiency and the ability of the ports to operate commercially.
So I think those are the key things.
Yes, there's an administrative burden, but it's unbalancing
what's already some quite
challenging commercial relationships with some very well-resourced
global companies. And there's the risk of the chilling effect
as well.
Thank you.
And the question from me, particularly, I don't know if you read the
Forest Owners Association submission, which has come-
I have to confess, I haven't
... virtually. Okay. But they've taken a case study in particular
of Port of Napier
around,
in this case, the smart flow fees.
One of the issues which has come up through the inquiry quite regularly has been
the issue of transparency around, it's mostly gate fees.
Mm-hmm.
I don't hear so much about the shipping fees.
But about transparency of fees, how they're set, et cetera.
The idea of whether the Commerce Commission might take an interest because there's
the
sort of pseudo monopolies or actual monopolies in some parts of the market.
Do you have a view on--
Because you've made the generous offer-
Yeah
... of saying, "Yes, we're interested in how we deal with transparency gaps."
Yeah.
If there's one, that seems to be the biggest one that we're hearing, I think.
Is there a commercial way?
Look, what I would say is they don't all operate on the same pricing model.
So it's a little bit difficult to compare apples with apples.
So some do charge that gate fee.
At least if you know what the fruit is, it helps.
Yeah. So some do charge that gate fee, some don't.
Eventually, those costs have to be covered somewhere.
Yes.
And each of the ports, they decide how they divvy it up.
And some of them charge gate fees, some of them just charge it straight to the
shipping lines.
And those are commercial. Some of them choose to publish their tariffs, and
that in itself is a commercial decision.
They might be trying to advertise that they think they're a bit cheaper than the
port down the road.
Mm-hmm.
Others negotiate
as they go. So look, I think it's worth a
further-- If you think that's an area that's worth some further interrogation,
very happy to continue that discussion.
But again, I return to the previous point that
logoima is not the right instrument to achieve the transparency that
you're looking for.
So my point of my question really was to try and understand the areas that
you thought were areas of possible discussion because you've made that
distinction.
Yeah. So I think, look, if there's further discussion about what the right
model for transparency around pricing is, I think we'd be very happy to engage in
that.
I think the key one is about network performance.
Mm-hmm.
If the ships are turning up on time and they're leaving on time,
everything else is detail Actually, so if you can rely on the ships
turning up on time, you can rely on them leaving on time.
The exporters are happy. They know what's going on.
Yep.
You can organize your workforce, et cetera.
So that sort of on-time performance, I think, is a really key piece.
Yeah.
Can I just add just to the end?
Whilst I don't dispute anything you've said, when people feel that they've been
left in the dark or there's a lack of information, that's a relationship issue
often, not just an information issue.
Yeah.
So it's all very well that the port CEs are
willing to do stuff-
Mm-hmm
... but I should
imagine that they've had plenty of opportunity to do so.
So
there's some good will to be built here.
Yeah. Look, my personal view is,
you do have a sort of wooly definition of what a successful business in the Port
Companies Act is.
My view is that
you don't get to be a successful business if you don't look after your people, if
you don't protect the environment, if you don't maintain your public license to
operate. You don't stay a successful business very long if you don't do those
things. So,
is there an argument for further clarifying what that means in the Port
Companies Act? I think you could. That's one area you could look at, and I think
that might be a more valuable piece, again, than extending logo.
Ian, thank you very much. That's very useful work.
Thank you.
Last year as well. Really appreciate it.
Okay, that takes us to the Taxpayers Union.
That's right.
Good morning, Mr. Chair, members of the committee.
Good morning. Good to see you.
Thank you for-
Thank you for submission.
So, thank you.
Same story, 10 minutes. We'll-
Yep.
If we will-
Thank you.
We love questions, and so I will hand over to you.
And again, we've got your submission, which you can take as read.
Yes. Thank you.
The Taxpayers Union supports the bill.
The basis for this is on the principle that public ownership should come with
public accountability.
This bill fits in with our objectives to increase transparency and
accountability for public entities and their subsidiaries.
Now,
the magnitude of the issue is actually quite important.
And,
Chair Foster, you touched on this in the
first reading debate, as recorded in
Hansard. Of the 11 major ports we've got, all of
them are at least partially council-owned.
Seven are fully council-owned, three are partially privatized,
and Eastern is owned by a community trust.
If you've got a fully council-owned entity that is looking at a major
investment, hundreds of millions of dollars of investment, that sometimes has a
material impact on ratepayers and directly on the risk that
ratepayers wear. We would agree with that completely.
12 ports are incorporated under the Port Companies Act.
The last analysis of value that was performed on a comparable basis
was that by the Auditor General using their 2019,
2020 financial information. The total asset value of these 12 port
companies came to 6.4 billion, with
total equity of 4.3 billion,
most of which is held by local and regional councils.
So ratepayers have a very, very significant, if not
100% stake in all of our ports.
There was much discussion in the Hansard about problem definition.
Hansard records a number of objections to the bill.
The principle objection is that there is no rationale for the bill, there is no
problem definition, and that it is a solution looking for a problem.
Secondary concerns revolve around information sensitivity as ports are commercial
entities, and to some extent, do compete
with each other.
But it's hard to demonstrate there is a problem when there is
no information available. Port companies have never been
subject to Logoima,
so there's no register of decline requests, no ombudsman case
file, no paper trail.
And that is not because nothing has gone wrong, but because the
one mechanism that would generate that evidence has never
applied to the ports.
Absence of a documented problem is not the same as absence of a
problem. In this case, it's close to a predictable
consequence of the exemption itself.
Commercial sensitivity issue is
quite important and again, the previous speaker raised this.
Auckland Transport and Water Care are both commercially exposed
council controlled organizations and both already operate under
Logoima. They use the Act's existing withholding grounds to
protect genuinely sensitive material every day.
The bill would not require port companies to be doing anything different.
The bill only brings port governance into line with
comparable public assets.
Now, I just want to talk a bit about a couple of, what you might call,
case studies.
In the Auditor General report
on the audits of the 2019, 2020
port companies, previous investment strategies have
not delivered as expected. This is most notable for Lyttelton Port
Company, where 290 million of assets were written down over
the last five years, in part because the expected revenue
associated with the new investment did not eventuate.
Christchurch ratepayers who wore that loss had no
avenue to demand further information to find out who
knew what and when did they know it.
This reduces transparency and frustrates the ability of
those financially impacted to hold responsible
those fully accountable.
Ports of Auckland
Ports of Auckland ran a container tunnel automation project from
2016 to 2022. The company wrote off 65
million when it was abandoned, with a further 16 million in conversion
costs to come. And as one Auckland councilor put, the
wider economic cost, including congestion and lost custom, at close to
half a billion dollars.
So very much not chicken feed.
The governance failures behind it only came to light through an independent
review the mayor specifically commissioned after the project
had already collapsed, not through any request ratepayers,
journalists, or councilors could have made themselves while the project was still
running.
The review found poor senior management engagement and weak accountability
throughout the project, and this is a particular bugbear of the Taxpayers
Union. It's the weakness of governance in
public entities. And we're seeing this on a daily
basis. The
Governance and Administration Committee is looking at fire and emergency.
We've got the unfolding scandal at MB.
And these organizations are actually covered by the Official
Information Act.
Now we get onto a more serious issue.
Four Ports of Auckland workers died between 2017 and 2022.
A 2021 independent review, again triggered by public and union pressure
rather than through any statutory right to information, found a workplace
culture that prioritized productivity over safety.
A former chief executive was later criminally convicted over one of the deaths.
So real harm to a ratepayer-owned asset was only discovered through scrutiny
that had to be specially arranged rather than exercised as of
right. Similarly, the root cause of worker deaths was only
discovered through a special investigation.
Had earlier access to this information via a LGOIMA
request been available, perhaps one or more deaths might have
been avoided.
So why is this bill necessary? This bill closes a structural
information gap between the public who own these assets and
the people who run them on a daily basis.
This is the same logic that requires audited financial statements without needing
prior proof of fraud. The Ports of Auckland and Lyttelton
cases simply show that the gap costs when it
runs unchecked for long enough.
The absence of public scrutiny of the actions of those entrusted with the
stewardship of public assets with substantial value is a
severe weakness in the port sector.
The loss in value, and worse, loss of life, may have been reduced
with earlier public disclosure that this bill facilitates.
It's important this bill progresses into law.
Thank you for your time.
Right, thank you very much. Really appreciate that. Dan, you had a question?
Yeah, thanks, Mr Chair. Thanks for your submission today.
In your submission, the core of your argument is in from
10 to 12,
essentially three key points.
You could make those same three key points with respect
to any entity in mind, with respect to Kiwi Bank, Air
New Zealand. Yeah, so I guess my initial question off the bat is
applying that your same logic, you would then
want to apply the same rules to
entities like Kiwi Bank and Air New Zealand, is that correct?
Exactly, yes.
Okay.
That would facilitate, I think, a lot more transparency and
accountability.
Okay. Secondly is, the core of your argument is
around, if I can recall,
a lack of democratic or weakness of governance.
Have you thought about
perhaps, to Andy's point a couple of submissions ago around halfway
houses, around
not applying the Official Information Act request,
but other sorts of ways we can boost
governance and strengthen governance in these entities?
I think in the first instance,
it's getting more disclosure.
The previous
submitter talked about a lot of corporate documents
that are available,
and that's true. But a lot of those are very,
very heavily massaged
to present a particular picture that
the
corporation would like to project.
What we're looking for is a level of disclosure that's
underneath that.
So we're not talking about stuff that's commercially sensitive,
but we're looking at
getting disclosure of the documents that
attest to particular corporate behaviors.
And in particular,
in the Ports of Auckland issue with the worker deaths,
it's
much greater disclosure of health and safety plans, operating procedures,
stuff that's not regarded as commercially sensitive.
But
my view is if they had been subject to LGOIMA,
the media would have been in really fast
and
digging through all of this. And as I pointed out, we may
have prevented one or two deaths,
which is quite significant when you think about the failure of
non-disclosure.
Tracy.
So
amongst many things that you were saying, the one that I kind of focused in on
was that it's not just about information
or voluminous information or the burden of information.
It's about the regime in place-
Yes
... that forces
I'll be thinking about the concept of releasing information and what-
Yeah. It's one thing to say XYZ in
your public corporate documents.
Mm.
But you have to
be acting in a way that supports
those public disclosures.
Mm.
And getting at the information from behind-
Yeah
... is the important step.
Mm.
And at the moment, the port companies,
are not subject to it. You can't do it.
The press could not get and demand, as of right,
health and safety data.
So even internally, the ports may not be as
cognizant of the information that they hold because they're in
no way, shape, or form forced to present it in a
manner that causes some digestion of themes or-
Yeah.
It's even internal correspondence-
Mm
... about
what the port knew about this death or that death.
This stuff only came out once the mayor's
investigation started-
Mm
... and the investigators had basically the authority to
demand all of that material, and of course, the finding at
the end was actually really quite shocking.
Mm.
And this goes back again to the basis that
the port companies are required to act
as profitable businesses, but they're subject to a constraint,
which is the health and safety constraint.
Mm. Thank you.
A couple of questions from me. First of all, just start with the health and safety
one.
And accepting your point that, if you start intervening
partway through the process, you might have had a correct-
Mm
... trajectory in terms of the
we have four deaths over a period of time.
But in terms of the investigations, there would've been an investigation anyway by
health and safety.
Oh, yes.
So they would've done that. That would've become pretty transparent,
or very transparent anyway, I would imagine.
So they would be held to account in that way.
That's a fair point.
What I don't understand is then why
the mayor then
demanded,
and what I'm taking something-
Was that before or after the other one?
No, it was after the fourth death.
It was after, yeah.
No.
No, after the health and safety.
Yeah.
So I can't answer that.
Can't answer for the mayor why he did that.
Neither can I. I'm not an HSE specialist either.
Yeah. Okay. Look, the other one you mentioned was you talked about Watercare and
AT. Well, AT
disappearing, obviously.
Yes.
But Watercare, and then you talked about Air New Zealand and Kiwi Bank,
and also ports. Aren't they operating in completely different environments?
Watercare has to have commercial relationships, obviously, but
those commercial relationships are with contracts or suppliers who are working
for it. It would be the dominant party there, I'm sure.
But with the others, Air New Zealand, Kiwi Bank, they're definitely not dominant
parties in their... Well, certainly internationally for Air New Zealand.
They're not dominant parties in a very competitive market that they're in.
That's right.
Ports likewise, you heard the maid just a few
moments ago on behalf of port CEOs, the scale between Port of
Tauranga and Maersk, for example.
Yeah.
Again,
they're not necessarily holding the whip hand.
So aren't they in different environments that they're operating?
And I know you'll probably tell me that the commercial sensitivity, you can deal
with that, no problem. But you've still got to walk your way through that.
You've still got to be subject to appeals and lagooners and, I'm sorry, appeals and
ombudsman and so on.
Yeah.
Aren't they different?
Yes, they operate in different environments.
Some in much more competitive environments, some pseudo
monopolistic,
some totally monopolistic.
The issue for us is
the public has significant investment in these
entities
and
therefore, there should be much greater public accountability.
The only way to achieve that is to have more public
transparency.
And that takes me to my last question, which was, so some of them, you've
said, and your view is different here to particularly the union's view,
that this
is because of public investment in them.
Yes.
The union's view is that it doesn't matter whether they're private or not, keep
them all on the same level playing field between ports.
Even if the one was completely privatized, not something we would support, but even
if one was completely privatized, you'd still make it subject to the same local
employment process, even if it has no local government ownership.
Does it become different for you if a company is entirely private as
opposed to if it is-
Yes
... partially it does become different?
Yes, it is. Yes.
Yeah.
Yeah. Again, it goes back, it's
public asset, public accountability.
Yeah. Okay. That is clear. Thank you very much. Really appreciate it.
All right.
Thank you.
Thank you for your time.
Okay.
And then
finally, we have the Forest Owners
Association. Welcome.
Kia ora.
Lovely to have you here.
And thanks again. Again, we've got a submission, which you could take a read, but
anything you want to say, that's great, and we will ask questions.
I know I've got quite a few from-
Great
... Elizabeth.
Thank you very much, Chair. Kia ora koutou.
I'm Elizabeth Hay. I'm the CEO of Forest Owners Association, and this is
our Chief Operating Officer, Joseph Brolley.
We're here today to talk to you about the bill on behalf of commercial
forest growers,
who export about $6.5 billion
annually over our ports in wood products
and logs.
Look, overall, we support the bill
We really want to see an improvement in transparency
and require that ports have,
I guess, more transparency, particularly around fee setting and
how they're conducting their businesses.
We've experienced, certainly, we've got a number of
forest exporters over the past few years that have experienced very
sharp increases in their
port charges without a lot of evidence of what that's
going to.
It's a time as well, and I guess you'll all be sensitive to this, of
geopolitical instability.
And as an exporting nation, we really need to
understand exactly how we're working together in order to ensure
that
in a very geopolitically
unstable environment with a lot of volatility, that we're not
also holding that volatility and lack of
transparency here at home. So with that, I will hand over to
Joseph to talk in more detail about some of our concerns.
Good morning. Thank you for the opportunity to speak today.
We strongly support the bill on the basis that public ownership should also
bring public accountability. Port companies are either
majority or wholly owned by local authorities, and they should be subject
to law and other social responsibility objectives like other
council-controlled organizations.
In terms of forestry's experience, our view is that export ports are
effectively regional monopolies.
For most forest owners, exporting through the local regional port is the only
commercially viable option. They cannot economically switch to another port in a
neighboring region due to the transport differential.
So we're effectively a captive market, and without competition and incentives to
innovate,
it's natural for monopolies to continually increase prices and adopt a cost
plus model, which is what we're seeing.
Just touching on Elizabeth's point before, port charges have increased
significantly over the past three years for forestry, far exceeding
inflation. We commissioned an independent report across all 13 log
export ports. Engaging with the ports turned out to be a
difficult and complex exercise. More on that later.
Our report found that in the three years from 2022,
charges to forest companies had increased between
16 and 54%, depending on the port.
Five of the ports, they had increased their charges from 30 to
54%, so very substantial. In addition to that, there's a
new pattern we've identified, which is new
charges being
continually added. So we've seen the environmental charges,
infrastructure charges, and insurance charges recently.
And we've also been suffering under the burden of truck access fees and most
recently the prospect of new dredging levies.
So, this pattern is not sustainable for forestry
and is not something that we think is reasonable.
There's a contagion effect of new charges across ports.
As soon as it's applied on one, it tends to spill over into other
ports.
And just to give you a case study of what these new charges can look
like, the smart flow truck access levy at Napier Port is a good
example. So, in 2024,
they pitched the service to industry as
a service to improve logistics and throughput times at the port.
There's a $15 fee to access the eastern gate at Napier
Port. Despite negative feedback from industry, it was
implemented in 2024,
and 12 months later, Napier Port had collected 1.34 million
in forestry fees,
in
smart flow fees from forestry with no demonstrable improvement in service
levels.
We see it as a simple revenue collection exercise, and if a similar
fee was implemented across all of New Zealand at other ports, it would cost the
industry $10 million.
The FOA wrote to Napier Port requesting removal of the charge on the basis that
none of the stated benefits had materialized, and Port declined to remove
the charge, noting that they were working in the best interests of shareholders
and they were not making adequate acceptable market returns.
But overall, the key
takeaway is that the increase in costs are very
significant for forestry. We export over 20 million tons equivalent
per year.
And these increase in port charges come at a time when forestry is facing
significant commercial headwinds and rising costs across the supply chain,
combined with flat or falling real prices.
I might just pause there.
Yes.
How much time do we have remaining?
We've got about four and a bit minutes.
I will take a fraction longer, but yeah, I would like to get to questions as
quickly as possible.
Okay, I'll obviously be very quick.
We've experienced a lack of accountability and transparency from some of the ports.
Getting the ports to engage in the benchmarking exercise was complicated.
Only six of the 13 agreed to participate in the interviews and share
data. And the ports are very quick to point out that
forestry companies have signed non-disclosure agreements and that they wouldn't be
able to disclose pricing information.
We thought this is a heavy-handed approach and inherently
anti-competitive. So what's proposed by the bill,
by extending law to apply to ports would help us to have better access to
information and provide more clarity on justification behind
decision making. And we're very supportive of
the social responsibility objectives,
the suggestion that port companies cannot justify any and all actions
by reference to acceptable return.
Cool.
Thank you.
Thank you. Right. Okay, questions.
I'll kick off then. The first one of them I've got is, you've made the comment
in your written submission, it's at seven,
extraction of excess profits from local forestry businesses.
And I just wonder what you-- because the general pattern that we've heard from
ports, and I think that we've observed from studies of ports, is the fact that the-
Is your time's obviously different mine.
The general pattern is actually the return on assets is relatively low.
It's often in the two, three, 4% type range,
which is hardly excess profits. So can you just substantiate what you're talking
about with that comment?
Well, in terms of Napier Port, for example, we note that they're making record
profits this year, and they note that a rise in levies have been one of the key
drivers of that port.
No. So might just stop you there, because my question is, you might increase the
profit significantly, but you've increased it from a return, which is if you had a
1% return and you increased the charges to give you a 3% return, you're still not
making an excess profit.
Yeah.
Now, you might want to get behind those numbers, but that's why I might say
specifically that word, excess profit.
Well, it's our view that the return on investment issue, because
the port assets are priced typically annually
and continually go up in value, the return on investment needs to
continually increase, so the charges need to increase, and it's our view that
there's not an incentive to provide innovation and
getting better and faster and that the asset
value is increasing, but a return on investment might
not seem acceptable to forest for the ports.
But our view is that there's actually ex- we can't see even as we
don't know if it's monopoly pricing, excess pricing or not.
Look, for us as well, part of this is really like we've
got businesses that are struggling to stay afloat
in significant economic headwinds.
And if they can't shop around, they can't take stuff to
other ports because especially with the fuel price increases and the
transport cost increases, actually forests that are 100
kilometers or more from a port right now are becoming uneconomic to harvest.
So when you look at then the port costs increasing and the
decrease in wood processing, like we're ending up with where are we going to
actually take our produce in order to be able to sell it.
And that's going to significantly impact on the ability of us to
attract further wood processing investment.
Transparency would help a lot. If we could more fully understand where the pricing
was coming from, that's one thing, but this is one of the death by a thousand
cuts that we're seeing across the forestry and wood processing sector.
So that's exactly where I was going to go is you've heard the compensation
before about whether it's at whatever level of touch it is from some sort of thing
like the Commerce Commission. You've heard the offer from the ports,
on behalf of the port CEOs, that some level of transparency somewhere, and
obviously the thing for you is the pricing. That will be helpful.
Very helpful.
Absolutely.
Yeah.
But I guess our experience has been, it's very patchy across the ports, how that's
implemented. So if it's a voluntary measure-
At the moment it's voluntary, yes
... we've got less confidence that that's going to flow through to all of the
ports.
Yes. No, I hear the point.
The other
area,
I think you kind of answered it, but you see the port charges increase between 16
and 54, but you said that five of them were at 30
plus in that period of time. Okay. And just these
various other levies that are coming through, so you've mentioned compliance,
insurance, and environmental, I think, infrastructure,
dredging.
When these are proposed by any given port, to what degree is there
transparency around this is what those charges are for,
and why they are not covered already by the existing charging
regime?
We struggle with exactly that issue, and we find
there's a lacking of transparency and openness and even
engagement on those issues. And in fairness, in
Napier Port, the smart flow levy example, they did engage with industry, and
they just went ahead despite our advice, which is their prerogative, but
yeah. Our view is that it's hard to justify
if we're not seeing any improvement of service
benefit, and it just looks like a revenue extraction exercise.
Yeah. Okay, cool. I'll just see if I had any others there that I think I have.
Just in terms of
one of the areas, just in terms of charging, one of them, and it's particularly
Auckland in this case, is charging to change
behavior. Now, Auckland doesn't do forestry,
because obviously doesn't work there in miles away.
But the idea of actually saying, well, look, we'd like to have, conceptually the
idea of saying we'd like to have instead of having everybody turn up at peak time
when the traffic's abysmal in a place like downtown Auckland, you don't want
that. So to say we're going to put a differential charge on if you turn up at peak
time versus off-peak time, which essentially is a time of use charge.
Do you have any difficulty? And that's not recovering a cost, but it's trying to
send a message which is come
now, not now.
Yeah. Good point. Auckland is an outlier, and they
technically do log export, but it's containerized, which is
very different to the rest of the ports.
Yeah.
And the volumes are very small.
Yes.
So it's kind of skewing it.
Yes. Okay.
Yeah.
But in the principle, I think what we're saying as well to the
ports is rather than use some kind of logistics
charging, we've got extensive kind
of trucking and
industry good networks that we can work through to optimize
logistics. If logistics is a problem, adding a charge, you're
just driving us kind of further into the red and making it harder for
businesses to operate. Let's work together collaboratively in a
business partnership as opposed to trying to use charges to drive behavior.
Well, let's say, I'm going to finish with this one.
Let's say you've done that, you've engaged with
the
business community and said, "Look, we've got an issue here with congestion.
We need to change it." The business community says, "Well, we're not going to
change behavior at all. We're going to keep on coming at the same time regardless."
Who's that on? Is it on the port or is it on the businesses?
I think it's a little bit on both. Smart Flow was introduced in the wake of
the significant Gisborne storm events when some of the reason there was so much log
traffic is because of recovery from wood debris and
where there had been blowovers of forest.
So where we've got significant events as well, that's an even more critical time-
Okay. That's fair
... for us to be able to work together.
But I'm talking about in principle.
Don't businesses have some sort of
obligation at least to look about how they respond to a situation which they're
imposing? Because otherwise, businesses are imposing that cost also on every other
person that's using that road.
No, totally appreciate that, and that's why we do all this industry good work to
try and coordinate and make sure that we're not putting that impost on the port.
That is a fair point, and industry works hard to make sure the
scheduling of trucks works so they're not all surging at the same time, and it's
not causing congestion. It's something that we're very aware of, and we don't want
to be interfering with the public use of roads and so on around
ports. And nor do we want our trucks to be delayed, so there's quite a strong
incentive to be efficient and keep logistics running smoothly.
And it
is challenging in terms of the
loading sequences that happen throughout the day, and it's quite hard in the
forestry sector to have a time window of 30 minutes when there's
all these things that happen in the forest.
Yeah. No, look, fair enough, but at least if it's on the radar screen, that's
helpful. Look, really appreciate the submission, really appreciate you coming along
and talking to us, and thank you very much.
Thank you.
Cool. Right. We are into
Brian next now.